so bante I've been practicing for many
years and there's one thing I just can't
seem to
overcome I've endured childhood a
certain childhood trauma and it still
haunts me flashbacks of those events
persist leading me to mistrust the world
and anticipate further
pain it's the reason why I got into
Buddhism causing and this also causes me
to avoid relationships and become
increasingly introverted how can I enjoy life and
introverted how can I enjoy life and
live with greater
ease well that's your problem really
right there so you can't be
practicing the D rightly and enjoying
the life in the sense of relationships
and the world the world is the
Peril suffering Bond trap all of that so
even even if you had no childhood
traumas if you actually want to practice
them rightly that should be taking you
in the direction of abandoning all
relationships abandoning the world
abandoning any ease that you find on
account of that world CU it's not
safe you're finding safety in the
burning house so my answer to this person is
house so my answer to this person is
really you need to kind of learn a bit
more about
actual goals of dhama and then clarify
your own goals in regard to it CU it
seems that you want to have both you're
practicing the Dharma to overcome the
trauma so that you can really enjoy the
life that's not the Dharma you're
practicing because the if you even if
you're practicing DH on account of a
trauma you would be overcoming the
trauma by overcoming the
world that your trauma depends on that
your trauma lives in and if you overcome
the whole world the whole possibilities
of world the Future No past trauma can
touch you the reason why people are
still under the thumb of the traumas is
because they refuse to relinquish the
world they refuse to relinquish the
senses sense organs dependence on
relationships joys of the world and
sensuality so you keep yourself inside
of the the the Hunt is Forest so you're
going to be hunted still and and the
Past Times you got caught and stuff will
be always applicable it will always
bother you cuz you refuse to give it all
up and the person uh this person thinks
that that the joys is the sentral pleasures
that the joys is the sentral pleasures
in the world the joys the relationships
that's that will cure no that's somehow
that's what I mean those things in and
of themselves are already afflictions
even if you had no specific traumas to
talk about dependent on being dependent
mentally for your well-being for your
safety on uh on the joys of the world on
the pleasures of the sense organs and
senses that's like the most perilous
thing you can do that is the truth true
Affliction so in a way if somebody had a
trauma that then turn him towards dhama
that's actually a fortunate thing but
it's unfortunate that they maybe have
not really come across the right
instruction of their dharm so they still
under the impression that they can do
both they can practice practice the
Dharma to the extent of not being
bothered by this specific Trauma from
their childhood but at the same time enjoy the
childhood but at the same time enjoy the
life and so on that the world that is
basically the trauma in and of
itself it's kind of interesting that you
know you have this trauma and the World
shows itself to you exactly exactly if the if
itself to you exactly exactly if the if
the world was a good place traumas would
not be
possible and fundamentally again if you
feel like oh I'm so unfortunate like
other people were not other people were
not traumatized in the past but I was
well they haven't been traumatized
yet maybe not in the childhood but they
will be traumatized sickness is a trauma
old age is a trauma failing senses is a
trauma death is the ultimate trauma that
nobody can avoid so from that point of
view all the other traumas are fairly
circumstantial because death is the
chief of all traumas that's waiting
everyone and that is again you would be
affected by that if you still do not
relinquish that
world so don't think of traumas in in in
in in a way that oh this these are the
things that I must deal with
specifically think of traumas as
symptoms that reveal you the real nature
of your situation which is you are
liable you were liable to traumas you
are liable to pain you're liable to
suffering and you will have to meet
those things
eventually unless you abandon your
entire dependence on sense organs sense
Pleasures the world the joys the
relationships and everything that come
from it so you have a choice if you stay
there you then have to just accept the
fact that you're going to be hunted down
by circumstances by unpleasant feelings
and eventually caught up with or if you
don't then then you will actually at
least try and apply yourself rightly in
the sense of the correct practice of the
Dharma and abandon it once and for all